Did you figure out what the problem was?
Let’s trace through this code and see where
the list went awry.
The first three lines of the code are acceptable.
But think of what happens on line 4.
When we remove Juneau, every list item to
the right of Juneau moves left one position.
I will type a comment on the right to simulate
what is happening here.
When Juneau is removed, the list becomes Montgomery,
Phoenix, LittleRock with no space, and Sacramento.
What position is Little Rock in now?
Position 2.
Thus, we need to make one of two changes to
fix this code.
Either we need to change the position on line
6 to position 2, or move the line of code
in front of line 4 so that Little Rock is
changed first and then Juneau is removed.
I will do the first change since it involves
less change.
You may have times when you need to remove
an item from a list, but save the value that
has been removed and use it in code.
For example, someone may remove a tool from
a toolbox, and you may want to display the
name of the tool that has been removed.
The pop method removes the last item of a
list but allows one to use it in code just
after removing it.
I will add a line in front of the print statement
on line 7 and type
print(capitals.pop()).
This statement will remove Sacramento from
the list and display it.
I will rerun this code, and we will see the
popped item and the remaining items in the
list, the remaining three state capitals.
You can specify an index number to pop a specific
item.
For example, if I add a 0 between the parentheses,
the first item on the list, Montgomery, will
be popped.
I will rerun the code, and we see the popped
city and then the remaining cities in the
list.
Sometimes, you want to sort a list or reverse
the order in which a list is displayed.
Reversing a list does not sort it in descending
order.
Reverse and sort are two different methods.
I will add a reverse method above the print
statement on line 7 to demonstrate this difference.
The statement looks like this: capitals.reverse().
Then, I will rerun the code, and the list
of cities prints in the reverse order in which
the list was entered and then manipulated.